[Music]
hi uh when I was asked if I would come
and give a TED Talk I was really happy
because I've been trying to give one for
a long time and uh then I asked what's
the subject and they said
Enlightenment and uh I started to think
about Enlightenment and for me enlighten
it it does in my mind I see some kind of
light come on in my mind and I see it uh
first I see it like a halo around a
person and then later I think I see it
as light inside of a person and then if
one of us has a lot of light inside uh
kind of Enlightenment inside and then it
would spread from person to person so
what I'd like to talk about today is is
it possible to become enlightened
ourselves one person and and then do we
really have a chance to make the whole
world enlightened is it possible for
each one of us to make the whole world
enlightened we love these uh superhero
movies Iron Man Spider-Man Batman
Fantastic 4
Wolverine H Wonder Woman we all would
like to be a superhero but what are the
chances that you and I can become a
superhero in this life and I think uh
there is a chance to become and there's
a chance for each person to be
enlightened
and to make the world enlightened so
today I'd like to talk about that
possibility I think there are like five
goals in life that people would like to
have one I like to call Financial
Independence I would like to have enough
money to do anything I want to do I
would like to have enough money to
really help the refugees in Europe you
know and around the world I would like
to have a lot of money and be
independent I don't want a big house
because I don't want to clean a big
house and I don't want a big car cuz
it's hard to park
you know I want small simple beautiful
things but about money I don't want to
think about money I want to have so much
money I don't have to think about it so
for me that was the first goal
financially independent then secondly I
think you can be rich but you can be a
lonely rich person and I think all of us
would like to have a a beautiful
partnership a beautiful family I think
relationships are the second goal of a
human life it's the happiest thing in a
human life if it's going well it's the
worst thing in human life if it's not I
think the third goal is good health uh
all of us would like to be young we
would like to be strong we would like to
be healthy not
sick these are all outside goals I think
inside with with financial Independence
you know with a beautiful relationship
with great energy then inside I would
like to be peaceful and I would like to
be like in a state of peace all the time
this is the inner goal I think those are
four things that everyone would like to
have and then fifth which we've heard in
today a very beautiful Talks by many
people I would like to do something to
help the world you know I I would like
to bring those four things that kind of
Enlightenment to the rest of the world I
would like to share what I have with the
rest of the world so I'm going to teach
you four quick steps that they taught me
in the monastery these come from the uh
4th
century and these are how to plan
a seed in your mind for things that you
want to achieve first I'll ask you some
questions just answer me this is the old
Tibetan system what is this thing
sharpen yeah it's a pen okay next
question if a small dog comes in here
and I go like this and I show this to
the dog what will they do with it chew
on it yeah they right it do they see
this as a pen no they see it as
something to Che next question who's
correct the human or the
dog yeah you could say both are correct
the human can ride the dog can chew most
important question if I come here and I
put this thing here and all the dogs go
out of the room and all the humans go
out of the room at that moment what is
this
thing pen or chew toy she has the best
answer she's going like this you know
and that's correct answer right then
it's almost like nothing in Buddhism we
call this emptiness if you understand
emptiness you can make anything happen
you can make a $250 million company you
can help refugees you know you can do it
if you understand emptiness what do
emptiness
means if the human comes back in the
room and they walk up here and they look
at this thing what does it
become it becomes a pen again okay did
that pen come from the human or did that
pen come from the
pen the human from the human if the dog
walks in it changes it becomes
a CH toy okay so the the pen is coming
from me if I close my eyes and wish I
had a diamond in my hand will it change
no no okay it's not by wishing there's
something in my mind which is forcing me
to see it as a pen in Buddhism we call
that Karma okay there's a seed in my
mind when I look at this thing the seed
opens in my mind and it forces me to see
a pen who put the seed in my
mind we say only you can put a seed in
your mind how do you put a seed in your
mind you go to another person you say I
have a pen do you want a pen and you
give it to them when you open your hand
and give them a pen or money or Refugee
Aid or whatever when you release the pen
and you open your hand who sees your
hand
open I see my
you see your hand open and the other
person sees your hand open when you open
your
hand that image goes into your mind and
it creates a seed in your mind okay when
you give something to someone else with
the intention of helping them with love
then this this creates the record in
your mind of that opening of your hand
creates an image and that image comes
into your mind it presses on your mind
and it creates a seed okay then two days
later you go to a TED Talk Ted X talk
and the guy holds up this thing and that
seed opens in your mind and you see a
pen and then you're not a dog
okay I only have like one second left
there are four ways to plant a seed I'll
tell you very quickly okay it's you can
do it for money for $200 million you can
do it for a partner you can do it for
your health you can do it to help the
whole world okay there are four steps
and I I wrote it on a piece of paper for
you but our first one decide what you
want okay of the five of the five goals
I mentioned decide which one you want if
you don't know what you want put I don't
know what I want I want to know what I
want okay Second Step you must find
another person who wants the same thing
okay you must choose another person who
wants the same thing if you want a
partner you must locate a lonely person
okay that's a second step I'm not
kidding you cannot plant a seed on your
own you can you need another person to
plant a Karma okay third step take them
out once aw can help them okay I like
what we said about that can be emotional
support it doesn't have to be money it
can be love it can be concern it can be
helping the other person to get their
life together okay that's step number
three when you talk to them you hear
yourself talking and it plants a seed in
your mind okay that's called a Karma
that Karma can spay your mind for 100
years without opening okay and you know
people who've done nice things and
they've had a terrible life okay it's
because they didn't know how to put
water on the karma so that's step number
four and that's the last thing I have to
say the trick to making those seeds in
your mind open quickly and powerfully
$200 million are a beautiful partner for
your whole lifetime the trick is to when
you come home at night before you go to
bed you you put your head down on the
pillow and you do a small meditation
okay with your head on the pillow we
call it coffee meditation don't ask me
why uh and you think about the beautiful
thing you did for somebody else you
think about the good things you've done
for someone else and when you think
about them when you think about a Karma
it puts water on that Karma and the
karma opens in your mind quickly into
the things you dream of if you
understand that then those who want
money will be giving money to others and
being happy about it those who want
health or a partner will be giving those
things to others those who want inner
happiness will try to make other people
happy and that's how you change the
world and that's how you Enlighten the
world it's only by helping other people
thank you very much
[Applause]